<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Mobile Development Group Blog</title>
 <link href="http://sdsmdg.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://sdsmdg.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2014-12-31T13:44:12+05:30</updated>
 <id>http://sdsmdg.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name>Mark Otto</name>
   <email>markdotto@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Introduction To Android Development</title>
   <link href="http://sdsmdg.github.io/2014/12/31/introduction-to-android-development/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-31T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://sdsmdg.github.io/2014/12/31/introduction-to-android-development</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='introduction_to_android_development'&gt;Introduction To Android Development&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id='why_develop_for_android_'&gt;Why Develop For Android ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With over 1 billion Android devices already activated, Android represents an incredible opportunity for developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Android continues to grow beyond smartphones, it will become the brains behind invisible, ubiquitous cloud-connected computing. This is an introductory guide that will help you build awesome apps for smartphones and tablets today, and propel you towards exciting opportunities in Android&amp;#8217;s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='resources'&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many resources online that can help you getting started. Here we are listing a few that will provide you an introduction to this exciting world :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='video_tutorials'&gt;Video Tutorials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.udacity.com/course/ud853'&gt;Developing Android Apps&lt;/a&gt; - Created by Google and offered on Udacity, this course is a nice stepping stone if you have prior programming experience.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.udacity.com/course/ud849'&gt;UX Design For Mobile&lt;/a&gt; - Another one by Google, this course will help you understand the most important and immediately useful techniques and approaches used by great mobile UX designers&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.youtube.com/user/androiddevelopers/featured'&gt;Android Developers Youtube Channel&lt;/a&gt; - Videos containing demos, tutorials, and anything else related to Android development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='documentation'&gt;Documentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://developer.android.com/training/index.html'&gt;Official Android Developer Documentation&lt;/a&gt; - Highly recommended and something every android developer must refer to, weather a noob or a pro. Contains beginner level tutorials as well as referance of all classes for more advanced developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='blogs'&gt;Blogs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/android.html'&gt;Vogella Android Tutorials&lt;/a&gt; - Short and precise tutorials about development for Android: tools installation, debugging and using various features.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.androidhive.info/'&gt;Android Hive&lt;/a&gt; - Nice collection of tutorials, tips and hacks for android and game developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id='question_answer_forum'&gt;Question Answer Forum&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.stackoverflow.com/'&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; - Q/A forum for programmers. Most probably you will find the answer to your problem here. If not&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.google.com'&gt;There is always Google !&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
